{
	"questions": [{
		"question": "What is Marbury v. Madison?",
		"answer": "Marbury v. Madison, 5 U.S. (1 Cranch) 137 (1803), was a landmark U.S. Supreme Court case that established the principle of judicial review in the United States, meaning that American courts have the power to strike down laws and statutes that they find to violate the Constitution of the United States"
	}, {
		"question": "When wa the Marbury V. Madison case decided?",
		"answer": "In the year 1803 Mrabury is regarded as the single most important decision in American constitutional law"
	}, {
		"question": "Why is this case considered as landmark decision?",
		"answer": "The Court's landmark decision established that the U.S. Constitution is actual law, not just a statement of political principles and ideals, and helped define the boundary between the constitutionally separate executive and judicial branches of the federal government"
	}, {
		"question": "What is the reason for this case and who were involved in rivalry?",
		"answer": "The case originated in early 1801 as part of the political and ideological rivalry between outgoing President John Adams and incoming President Thomas Jefferson.[3]"
	}, {
		"question": "Who believed the undelivered commissions were void?",
		"answer": "Jefferson believed the undelivered commissions were void and instructed his Secretary of State, James Madison, not to deliver them.[5"
	}, {
		"question": "Who is william Marbury?",
		"answer": "William Marbury, a Maryland businessman who had been a strong supporter of Adams and the Federalists"
	}, {
		"question": "Who filed lawsuit for writ of mandamus?",
		"answer": "Marbury filed a lawsuit in the Supreme Court asking the Court to issue a writ of mandamus forcing Madison to deliver his commission"
	}, {
		"question": "what is Section 13 of the Judiciary Act of 1789",
		"answer": "Section 13 of the Judiciary Act of 1789 authorized the Supreme Court “to issue writs of prohibition to the district courts, when proceeding as courts of admiralty and maritime jurisdiction, and writs of mandamus, in cases warranted by the principles and usages of law, to any courts appointed, or persons holding office"
	}, {
		"question": "what is judicial review and how madison case was associated",
		"answer": "In Madison case, The Court then struck down Section 13 of the Act, announcing that American courts have the power to invalidate laws that they find to violate the Constitution—a power now known as judicial review"
	}, {
		"question": "Who favored agriculture and decentralization in 1800 election?",
		"answer": "Jefferson and Burr were leaders of the opposition Democratic-Republican Party, which favored agriculture and decentralization"
	}, {
		"question": "How many judges/supporters were part of the Midnight Judges",
		"answer": "60 supporters that includes William Marbury"
	}, {
		"question": "When was the case filed?",
		"answer": "December 1801, Marbury filed a lawsuit against Madison in the U.S. Supreme Court, asking the Court to force Madison to deliver his commission"
	}, {
		"question": "Give details of Marbury v. Madison, 5 U.S. at 158, 160",
		"answer": "The [President's] signature is a warrant for affixing the great seal to the commission, and the great seal is only to be affixed to an instrument which is complete. ... The transmission of the commission is a practice directed by convenience, but not by law. It cannot therefore be necessary to constitute the appointment, which must precede it and which is the mere act of the President."
	}, {
		"question": "Marbury, 5 U.S. at 163",
		"answer": "The very essence of civil liberty certainly consists in the right of every individual to claim the protection of the laws whenever he receives an injury."
	}, {
		"question": "What is writ of mandamus",
		"answer": "a type of court order that commands government officials to perform an act their official duties legally require them to perform—was the proper remedy for Marbury's situation in this case"
	}, {
		"question": "Judiciary Act of 1789, Section 13",
		"answer": "That the Supreme Court shall have exclusive [original] jurisdiction over all cases of a civil nature where a state is a party ... [and] suits or proceedings against ambassadors, or other public ministers ... The Supreme Court shall also have appellate jurisdiction from the circuit courts and courts of the several states, in the cases herein after specially provided for; and shall have power to issue ... writs of mandamus, in cases warranted by the principles and usages of law, to any courts appointed, or persons holding office, under the authority of the United States."
	}, {
		"question": "U.S. Constitution, Article III, Section 2",
		"answer": "In all Cases affecting Ambassadors, other public Ministers and Consuls, and those in which a State shall be Party, the supreme Court shall have original Jurisdiction. In all the other Cases before mentioned, the supreme Court shall have appellate Jurisdiction, both as to Law and Fact, with such Exceptions, and under such Regulations as the Congress shall make."
	}, {
		"question": "Marbury, 5 U.S. at 176–77.",
		"answer": "The powers of the legislature are defined and limited; and that those limits may not be mistaken or forgotten, the constitution is written. ... Certainly all those who have framed written constitutions contemplate them as forming the fundamental and paramount law of the nation, and consequently the theory of every such government must be, that an act of the legislature, repugnant to the constitution, is void."
	}, {
		"question": "Marbury, 5 U.S. at 177.",
		"answer": "It is emphatically the province and duty of the Judicial Department to say what the law is."
	}, {
		"question": "Why Marbury Vs Madison case was a brilliant work of Marshall?",
		"answer": "[Marbury v. Madison] is a masterwork of indirection, a brilliant example of Marshall's capacity to sidestep danger while seeming to court it. ... The danger of a head-on clash with the Jeffersonians was averted by the denial of jurisdiction: but, at the same time, the declaration that the commission was illegally withheld scotched any impression that the Court condoned the administration's behavior. These negative maneuvers were artful achievements in their own right. But the touch of genius is evident when Marshall, not content with having rescued a bad situation, seizes the occasion to set forth the doctrine of judicial review. It is easy for us to see in retrospect that the occasion was golden, ... but only a judge of Marshall's discernment could have recognized it."
	}, {
		"question": "What are the other cases which Marbury V Madison case influenced?",
		"answer": "1974 decision United States v. Nixon, in which the Court held that President Richard Nixon had to comply with a subpoena to provide tapes of his conversations for use in a criminal trial related to the Watergate scandal, and which ultimately led to Nixon's resignation"
	}, {
		"question": "Why the case was deferred till 1803?",
		"answer": "Democratic-Republican Congressmen passed a bill that canceled the Supreme Court's 1802 term. This prevented all of its pending cases, including Marbury v. Madison, from being decided until 1803"
	}, {
		"question": "Give me citations from Marbury v Madison case",
		"answer": " Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 39. Chemerinsky (2021), § 1.3, p. 12.\nMcCloskey (2010), p. 25.\nChemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, pp. 39–40.\nPohlman (2005), p. 21.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 40.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, pp. 41–42.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 44.\n Epstein (2014), p. 89. McCloskey (2010), pp. 23–24.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 40.\n Brest et al. (2018), p. 115.\n Miller (2009), p. 44.\n Paulsen et al. (2013), p. 141.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 41.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 41.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 42.\n Amar (1989), p. 447.\n Amar (1987), pp. 1485–86.\n Amar (1987), p. 1486.\n Brest et al. (2018), pp. 124–25.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, pp. 42–43.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 41, quoting Marbury, 5 U.S. at 163.\n The Old Supreme Court Chamber, 1810–1860 (PDF). Office of Senate Curator (Report). U.S. Senate Commission on Art. June 24, 2015 [2014-02-10]. S. Pub. 113-3.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 43.\n Van Alstyne (1969), p. 15.\n Nowak & Rotunda (2012), § 1.3, p. 50.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 44.\n Fallon et al. (2015), pp. 69–70.\n Currie (1997), p. 53.\n Tribe (2000), p. 207.\n Tribe (2000), pp. 207–08."
	}, {
		"question": "Give me more citations from Marbury v Madison case",
		"answer": "Prakash & Yoo (2003), p. 914. Tribe (2000), p. 210.\n Quoted in part in Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 45, and Tribe (2000), p. 210.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 45.\n Quoted in Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 45.\n Nowak & Rotunda (2012), § 1.3, pp. 52–53.\n Tribe (2000), p. 210, quoting Marbury, 5 U.S. at 178.\n Quoted in Tribe (2000), p. 210.\n Nowak & Rotunda (2012), § 1.3, p. 53.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 46.\n McCloskey (2010), p. 26.\n Tribe (2000), p. 208, note 5.\n McCloskey (2010), pp. 25–27.\n Nowak & Rotunda (2012), § 1.4(a), p. 55.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, p. 46.\n Fallon et al. (2015), p. 69.\n Chemerinsky (2019), § 2.2.1, pp. 46–47.\n Nowak & Rotunda (2012), § 1.4(a), p. 54.\n Frankfurter (1955), p. 219\n Brest et al. (2018), pp. 133–34.\n Nowak & Rotunda (2012), § 1.4(a), p. 55."
	}, {
		"question": "Does Marbury have a right to the commission?",
		"answer": "Yes. Marbury has a right to the commission.The order granting the commission takes effect when president’s constitutional power of appointment has been exercised, and the power has been exercised when the last act required from the person possessing the power has been performed. This last act is the signature of the commission."
	}, {
		"question": "Does the law grant Marbury a remedy?",
		"answer": "Yes. The law grants Marbury a remedy.The very essence of civil liberty certainly consists in the right of every individual to claim the protection of the laws whenever he receives an injury. One of the first duties of government is to afford that protection.Where a specific duty is assigned by law, and individual rights depend upon the performance of that duty, the individual who considers himself injured has a right to resort to the law for a remedy.The President of the United States, by signing the commission, appointed Mr. Marbury a justice of the peace in the District of Columbia. The seal of the United States, affixed thereto by the Secretary of State, is conclusive testimony of the verity of the signature, and of the completion of the appointment. Having this legal right to the office, he has a consequent right to the commission, a refusal to deliver which is a plain violation of that right for which the laws of the country afford him a remedy."
	}, {
		"question": " Does the Supreme Court have the authority to review acts of Congress and determine whether they are unconstitutional and therefore void?",
		"answer": "Yes. The Supreme Court has the authority to review acts of Congress and determine whether they are unconstitutional and therefore void.It is emphatically the duty of the Judicial Department to say what the law is. Those who apply the rule to particular cases must, of necessity, expound and interpret the rule. If two laws conflict with each other, the Court must decide on the operation of each. If courts are to regard the Constitution, and the Constitution is superior to any ordinary act of the legislature, the Constitution, and not such ordinary act, must govern the case to which they both apply."
	}, {
		"question": "Can Congress expand the scope of the Supreme Court’s original jurisdiction beyond what is specified in Article III of the Constitution?",
		"answer": "No. Congress cannot expand the scope of the Supreme Court’s original jurisdiction beyond what is specified in Article III of the Constitution.The Constitution states that “the Supreme Court shall have original jurisdiction in all cases affecting ambassadors, other public ministers and consuls, and those in which a state shall be a party. In all other cases, the Supreme Court shall have appellate jurisdiction.”If it had been intended to leave it in the discretion of the Legislature to apportion the judicial power between the Supreme and inferior courts according to the will of that body, this section is mere surplusage and is entirely without meaning. If Congress remains at liberty to give this court appellate jurisdiction where the Constitution has declared their jurisdiction shall be original, and original jurisdiction where the Constitution has declared it shall be appellate, the distribution of jurisdiction made in the Constitution, is form without substance."
	}, {
		"question": "Does the Supreme Court have original jurisdiction to issue writs of mandamus?",
		"answer": " No. The Supreme Court does not have original jurisdiction to issue writs of mandamus.To enable this court then to issue a mandamus, it must be shown to be an exercise of appellate jurisdiction, or to be necessary to enable them to exercise appellate jurisdiction.It is the essential criterion of appellate jurisdiction that it revises and corrects the proceedings in a cause already instituted, and does not create that case. Although, therefore, a mandamus may be directed to courts, yet to issue such a writ to an officer for the delivery of a paper is, in effect, the same as to sustain an original action for that paper, and is therefore a matter of original jurisdiction."
	}, {
		"question": "Did Marbury get the commission?",
		"answer": "Marbury doesn’t get the commission."
	}, {
		"question": "Give me tokens for the Marbury v Madison case?",
		"answer": "appellate jurisdiction, Article III, case briefs, Constitutional Law, Judiciary Act of 1783, jurisdiction, law, news, opinion, writ of mandamus, doctrine"
	}]
}